We are currently at 298 K subs.
The goal is to get to 300 K by the end
of this month,
which would be a huge,
you know, milestone for me.
300 would definitely be nice, so every
sub counts.
And let's get the show on the road.
Black against 1324, very strong
opponent.
And we're going to play as is my
officially
recommended line, the accelerated
dragon. Hopefully we get a open
Sicilian.
Hopefully we get an open Sicilian. We're
praying for D4, but if we don't, that's
also valuable. You have to know many
anti-Sicilians.
Of course, there's the Rossolimo, Bishop
B5, and this is the first time we are
facing it.
So, Bishop B5 is called the Rossolimo
variation.
Uh
you can think of it almost as the Ruy
Lopez against the Sicilian.
And it is the favorite choice uh
among top players now for well over a
decade. I mean, Fabiano Caruana plays
the Rossolimo regularly. I myself with
the white pieces play Bishop B5 almost
exclusively. I almost never go D4.
And the benefit of the Rossolimo at a
high level is that it offers a more
positional game
uh in contrast to the open Sicilian, and
it is a very, very serious way to fight
for the advantage at a high level. Now,
at at a lower level, people often play
Bishop B5 without really understanding
why they're playing it. They just
sometimes think that they're playing the
Ruy Lopez, and they don't fully
understand the difference.
Now, since we are accelerated dragon
players in the speed run, we are going
to play the move G6 here. There are two
principal ways to play the Rossolimo
with black. G6 is one move, and as many
in the chat are indicating, the other is
E6. So, for people who play, let's say
the Paulsen,
or who play the Taimanov, e6 is a more
sensible choice. But for accelerated
Dragon players, it is more consistent to
fianchetto your Bishop. And in this
position, once again,
there is a choice between BC and DC.
And if if you think back
all the way to our initial speed run,
you might remember a couple of games
where we faced the Rossolimo.
And you might remember that the main
move for black is actually to play d
takes c6 to capture away from the
center. And that is what we're going to
do right now. It's a capture away from
the center.
But looking at DC just visually, you
should immediately begin to realize what
the motivation behind taking away from
the center is. There's a couple of
things to notice. The first, of course,
is that you're opening up the diagonal
for the Bishop. The second is that
you're opening up a line of contact
between the queen and important squares
on the D file. So, you were increasing
your control over the center
uh
by by recapturing with the D pawn.
Now, we complete our kingside
development with Bishop g7,
fianchettoing the Bishop.
And
in these types of positions, white often
plays the move h3. Like the players who
who are familiar with Rossolimo theory
end up playing h3
in order to prevent the move Bishop g4.
Uh but we don't have to play Bishop g4.
It's not like trading the Bishop for the
knight is really like that good for
black. It's just considered good from a
positional standpoint. But we're going
to play it in a much simpler way. I'm
going to try to illustrate the sort of
main Rossolimo ideas for black.
And
essentially, what we're trying to do
with black, first and foremost, is
we're trying to set our pieces up in
such a way
that we fully clamp down on the center.
And when you hear this word clamp,
right, clamp down, you should think very
often of two pawns
that are dominating, let's say, a key
square or a key set of squares. So, the
move that you should be kind of that
that should be circulating around your
mind
uh is e7 e5.
Uh upon which the bishop is kind of
considered an extension of the pawn. The
bishop and the pawn are one unit. And
what is that one unit doing? They are
controlling this very important d4
square. They're also controlling the f4
square. They're just basically
controlling key squares in the center.
Um but
before we push e5
it's a good idea to carry out the
following maneuver.
First, we're going to start by playing
knight f6. And we're going to develop
our knight uh to f6.
So, this is a very flexible move. That
doesn't mean that we're not going to
play e5. But what you're going to see is
that if white's bishop comes out to e3
our knight's going to drop back to d7
where it's going to be controlling the
c5 pawn, defending the c5 pawn, and
reinforcing the idea of e5.
And that is why you often see players in
the Ruy Lopez actually playing bishop g4
with black.
That's why you see players play players
playing bishop g4 with black because
the drawback of dropping the knight back
to d7
is of course that it locks in the bishop
on c8. And you might say, "Well, what's
the problem with then fianchettoing the
bishop to b7?" Well, there aren't that
many prospects on this other diagonal
because then it'll be hemmed in by the
c6 pawn.
So, if you want to play this like a
positional pro
we first play bishop g4, we trade the
bishop for the knight, then we drop the
knight back to d7, we push e5, and our
remaining two minor pieces are both
uh very much involved in the process of
controlling the center. Bishop takes f3.
There we go.
Now, we drop our knight back to d7.
And the reason we play knight d7 first
is that E5 immediately allows white the
additional option
of developing his Bishop to G5 and
trading the bishop off for the night.
This knight is an integral player in our
control over the center. And now
finally, we sort of complete our initial
central plan with the movie five.
Um hopefully
that has made sense. Now our opponent is
demonstrating complete knowledge of all
the key ideas, which is pretty
impressive. A4
White is grabbing some space on the
queen side.
Now we want to join the party. We don't
want to let white just advance this pawn
to A5 and clamp down our queen side. So
what should we do?
How should we Well, we should meet white
at the top.
What move does that entail?
So B6 doesn't actually prevent white
from playing A5. In fact, I would argue
that B6 makes A5 even more annoying. It
kind of gives some fuel to the fire. I
would just play A5. Yeah, just clamp it
down.
And prevent white from making further
progress on the queen side.
Yeah, so as buddy indicates in the chat,
our subsequent plan in this position is
to castle king side and then push F5 and
start a king side pawn attack.
Much like in a lot of openings like the
King's Indian Uh there a lot of openings
where you have this plan of pushing the
F pawn on the king side.
And that's another reason that we
fianchettoed our dark squared Bishop so
that when we push F5
uh we don't have to worry too much about
weakening our king side. 92 I mean, our
opponent is playing
a fantastic positional game so far. We
castle king side, of course.
And I assume our opponent is guiding his
knight toward G3 in order to prevent F5.
Wow, okay.
Well, we don't give up on our plans that
easily.
We don't give up on our plans that
How can we reinforce the idea of F5?
Well, ideally you would have like a
bishop that would be on E6 here. But, in
this case
you have to make do with what you have.
So, who can tell me like what piece
uh can we bring to what square?
And if you're watching on YouTube, try
to pause and figure this out in order to
reinforce the threat of F5. We have to
use the queen. We simply have to use the
queen. Now, from what square could the
queen prepare F5?
Well, it could prepare F5 from the E6
square.
So, let's start with the move queen E7.
Not queen C8. The problem with queen C8
is that the knight is blocking the
queen's access to F5, and then moving
the knight involves giving up the C5
pawn. So, you would have to additionally
play B6.
And then you have to move the knight
away to B8. That seems to be
uh rather cumbersome. Here, we already
put our queen on E6, and we are already
prepared to play F5.
Could you explain queen E7 over queen
E8? Well, the only reason I chose queen
E7 over queen E8
uh is that uh
it kept the rooks connected. That's
really all there was to it.
Our opponent is
preparing B4. Okay, let's think about
this for a second.
Yeah, this is far from easy, of course.
So, of course
candidate move number one is the move
F5. And F5 looks very appealing indeed.
It prepares a fork with F4.
But, the the genius of our opponent's
play
uh positioning the knight on G3 was
actually very smart from our opponent's
perspective. Because the move F5 can
actually be met with E takes F5, G takes
F5, and the knight can jump out to this
H5 square. And everybody should kind of
understand that that H5 square is is
rather annoying because it pressures the
bishop on G7.
And if the bishop in that position drops
back to h8, then there is another check
on g3. So, things kind of get a little
bit dicey on the king side. But, dicey
doesn't mean insurmountable or
unmanageable.
And I don't think that knight h5 is a
deal breaker. We've done all of this in
order to play f5. I think we should
follow through. We don't have much else
that we can do here.
Perhaps some of you noticed the move
queen to b3, but then white's queen can
drop back to d1.
And an end game is definitely not in
black's favor here given that we are the
one with a damaged pawn structure on the
king side on the queen side.
Okay, so far our opponent is playing
very, very well. Knight h5 here is what
I would play with white.
Not an easy move at this level, but I
think he's going to find it.
"This doesn't feel positional as black."
says Eric the Red. Well,
I I think saying something
does or does not feel positional is is
kind of relative. We're kind of
following the prescribed method in this
position. And I'm cutting some corners
with black. I will fully admit that the
way that I'm playing this position with
black is not how we're going to play it
when we're like 2,000, right? I'm just
trying to kind of illustrate the
skeletal basic plans in the position to
give you a sense of how to play.
Uh otherwise, it's very hard to teach,
you know, these conceptual openings like
the Ruy Lopez properly. If I kind of
throw all the theory at you, then you're
kind of going to get lost in the
complications. Hopefully, I've managed
to illustrate the general plans thus
far.
So, what are we threatening? Well, we're
threatening the move f4 that would fork
the two minor pieces.
Okay.
So, white can't just blindly follow
through with his plan of b4.
White has to move one of the minor
pieces.
Apart from f4,
we also have a rather
a rather uh extensive assortment of
improving moves. Like, for example, what
are some moves that we could play to
improve our position? Well, we could
bring the A rook into the game with rook
A to E8. And I always recommend on your
opponent's turn, if the position is not
overly tactical, to kind of generate
these lists of general improving moves
that you could play.
Uh, not only does that make your play
more efficient, but
it's kind of the prescribed method at
uh,
at at at a high level to think
conceptually on your opponent's turn,
and then think more concretely on your
own turn. I think that's a pretty good
way to apportion
the thinking time. Bishop to D2.
So, there's a couple of ways to handle
this position. We could play rook A to
E8,
but there is a move here that I actually
really like, and it's it's a move that I
think not a lot of players would
necessarily look at instinctually. It's
it's a move that offers a queen trade.
I'll give you a pretty big hint.
And the point of this move isn't just to
offer the queen trade, it's to fix the
queen side pawn structure, and to knock
off white's very nastily placed queen on
F3. This queen on F3 is is really well
placed for white, because it it it halts
the progress of our king side pawns,
and it it and it aims at the queen side.
So, if white ever plays the move B4, it
can combine with the rook to exert
pressure on our queen side.
So, the move I'm I have my eye on is
actually queen E6 to D5.
So, we have a positional threat of
taking white's queen and ruining white's
king side pawn structure. Not the end of
the world for white, but still a pretty
big gain if we're playing black.
If white plays knight takes F5, that
fails tactically, and you should see
that. Then, we take the queen on F3.
White has an intermediate check on E7,
but in that position, who can tell me
which way we go with our king?
So, in that position, do we go to H8 or
do we have a different square?
Simple calculation. Just testing your
visualization. Yeah, king F7, right?
That's a classic method where then white
has to waste the tempo taking back our
queen and the king takes the knight on
E7. We are up a piece.
So, knight takes F5, queen takes F3, G
takes F3, rook takes F5 wins the piece.
If white accedes to the queen trade,
then we get a massive pawn center. We
get four pawns on the fourth rank.
And in that situation, we'll be prepared
to continue steamrolling white with E4.
So, we're posing a rather difficult
decision to white and we're improving
the placement of our own queen.
Uh so, it's a it's a rather nasty
positional move uh to face, I think, for
white.
Hopefully, that explanation made sense.
Mamba on Discord asks, "Doesn't queen
takes D5 create a hole on B5?" It does.
I can't argue with that, but what can
possibly occupy that hole? Can you
envision a future where the white knight
on G3 gets to B5? Perhaps, but that's
going to take the knight at least
four or five moves and that's an
eternity in a chess game. Our
gains are a lot more immediate than the
hole on B5.
And remember, almost everything's going
to have some drawback. You're going to
be able to look at almost every move and
say, "Well, this creates a hole. This
creates a weakness."
Queen E2, best move, by the way, by our
opponent. That's very, very strong. Uh
keeping the queens on the board, our
opponent understands that that is the
way to keep fighting for the advantage
with white.
So, now we have to keep finding ways
to improve our position.
And I have a couple of ideas.
So, of course, I think the most obvious
move in the position, as many of you are
indicating, is in fact rook 8 e8.
But that's not the only way that we
could use our rooks uh to try to
pressure the king side.
Another interesting idea would be well,
if our rooks were doubled on the f file,
right? Let's imagine for a second that
we had rooks on f7 and f8, you might
then notice that you have this idea of
playing f4.
Now f4 is a positionally
very risky move. Why is it so
positionally risky? Because it gives up
this massive square in the center for
the knight. It gives up the e4 square.
But if the rooks were doubled on the f
file, then you would be able to push the
pawn all the way to f3 and provoke
massive weaknesses on white's king side.
It would probably be worth it to do so.
So one idea here is actually to play
either rook f7 or even rook up to f6.
And the reason
uh I like a move like rook f6 is from f6
the rook could perhaps double back to c6
and put some pressure on white's g2
pawn. So that would be an interesting
way to go.
But conversely, the benefit of playing
rook f7
is that the rook on f7 is a nice
defensive piece. It's kind of protecting
the bishop. It's protecting the king.
And it's also protecting the b7 pawn.
So I actually want to go for rook f7.
If you think about it, let's not forget
that white had this old idea of playing
b4. White plays c4. Okay.
That is music to my ears.
Because it's kind of one move-itis.
White attacks the queen, but white
weakens the d3 pawn. Now this is a
serious weakness. It's a backward pawn.
And correspondingly, there is now a very
juicy outpost that's been created on d4.
And our knight on d7 is only three moves
away from exploiting that outpost.
Knight f8, knight e6, and knight d4 is
going to pop probably come next. Where
should we move the queen? Should we move
it to d6? Should we move it to d6?
Or should we move it up to d4 and occupy
the outpost?
Well, you should rule out queen d4. You
shouldn't occupy outposts with a queen
because it's way too vulnerable. You
should drop it back to d6. This is the
nicest square because you're aiming at
the d3 pawn. Queen e6 would kind of step
into the pin
and it would allow a nasty move like f4,
which by the way, white could play
anyway. I would maybe even play f4 with
white.
But the queen on d6 is clearly the best
of the three squares available to the
queen.
How do I see these knight moves? Well,
it's not that hard, right? It's It's
just all about charting a course. You
notice the destination square and then
you just ask yourself, how do I get
there in the fastest possible way?
Now, we have to be careful
because there's this pawn on a5 which is
going to be hanging if we play rook e8
too quickly.
So, we should definitely consider
throwing in the move b6 in order to
reinforce the a5 pawn so that we don't
have to worry about that headache. Of
course, we could sacrifice the pawn on
a5. That is not out of the question if
we can,
you know, if we're desperate or if we
believe that uh the importance of
getting the knight, let's say, to d4
supersedes the importance of a par- par-
corner pawn, then we would sacrifice a5.
But I don't really see the need for that
in this position. I think we have the
luxury here of making sure that
everything is protected.
Um
so, we have a couple of candidate moves.
We can play knight f8,
but the problem with knight f8 is that
white's going to go rook f to e1.
And if we then go knight e6, we actually
drop this very important pawn on e5.
So, we can modify our strategy a little
bit. We can go knight f8, rook fe1, and
then we can go knight to g6. And knight
to g6 defends the pawn on e5 and also
aims for the f4 square. It's not as good
as the e6 square, but it's still a
pretty solid defensive square for the
knight.
We could also take a slower approach. We
could say, "Let's not move the knight at
all yet. Let's start with the move B6,
then let's bring the rook to E8. Let's
try to shore up all of our weaknesses
first, and then maybe later we'll have
an opportunity to get the knight around
to D4."
So, I think all of these options make a
lot of sense.
I think that we should probably try to
play as solidly as possible given that
our opponent is playing super well, so
let's play B6 and let's play rook E8 and
let's keep
as many of our options open for the
knight as possible.
Well, doubling rooks and going F4 is no
longer
the appropriate idea because if you play
F4, knight E4 now comes with tempo.
Right? So, we won't really be able to
shove this pawn all the way down to F3.
And if you think about it, after F4
knight E4, if you have to spend a tempo
moving your queen, you give white then
the opportunity to play the move F3
himself and close down the possibility
of us going F3, and we certainly don't
want to give away the C4 square for
free.
Okay?
So, we're just making general improving
moves right now. This is a stage of the
game in which you shouldn't like
overthink it. We're just bringing pieces
into the game. We're protecting our weak
pawns, and we're awaiting an opportunity
to make further improvements with our
minor pieces.
So, our next move most likely is going
to be rook A8 to E8 in order to
reinforce the pawn on E5.
And you might say, "Well, shouldn't we
reinforce the pawn on F5?" And we can,
but I have a feeling that at some point
white might be white might be likely to
play a move like F4.
And if he does do that, wouldn't we want
to have a rook on this file? If the E
file ever opens up, it's a good idea to
already have a rook there so that we can
fight for it. In addition, the actual
reason that I play rookie eight is so
that the knight is free to roam about
the cabin. We could not go knight f8
here because that would blunder the pawn
on e5. Whoop, that is none of those
arrows were accurate. White has one,
two, three attackers
and we would have only had two defenders
on e5. So, we're adding a defender in
order to be able to maneuver the knight
over to g6.
And the reason we'd maneuver the knight
to g6 is not just so that the knight
again defends e5, but rather as a
destination point as a transit point to
f4, Frankfurt Airport.
Yeah, one could say that we are over
protecting the e5 pawn to
use Nimzowitschian terms. And over
protection is just protecting something
more times than is strictly necessary
in order to free up pieces that are
currently defending the pawn. If
you're over protecting a pawn, that
means you don't need to be protecting it
as many times. That means some of the
pieces can go do other things. f4 played
by our opponent. Okay.
What we're going to do now
is try to exploit a drawback of the move
f4.
Now, it would be very nice, wouldn't you
agree,
if we could reposition our f rook to e7,
if we could double rooks on the e file.
Well, that would be pretty nice because
the e file is very likely to open, but
we can't do that because the pawn on f5
is going to be hanging. So, which piece
could we shift to what square? Yeah, and
a lot of you guys are already pointing
this out. Queen d6 to g6 is a nice way
of simultaneously attacking the knight,
which has been loosened by white's last
move, and
pro- uh protecting the f5 pawn, making
it possible for us to shift our rook to
e7,
which to remind you once again, we are
doing because the e file is very likely
to open up once white plays f takes e5.
Now, unfortunately, there's the very
annoying move knight H5, which
consistently with our opponent's level
thus far, he should be
should be well within his level.
And after knight H5,
I most certainly No, he plays queen F3.
Okay.
So, queen F3, I think allows us
to continue with our plan and play rook
F to E7, doubling our rooks on the E
file.
Now, as a consequence of that, we are
now able to move the E pawn. Previously,
we couldn't play E takes F4 because the
rook on E8 would be hanging.
Now, we have at our disposal two
possibilities. We can play E takes F4 or
in some cases we can push the pawn to
E4. F takes E5, our opponent strikes
first.
What should we recapture with?
Well, we can reach that calculationally
because if we take with the bishop, we
walk into knight takes F5.
And then if we take the knight in that
position, white plays knight takes E7
check, winning both of our rooks.
So, we have to take with the knight.
And the point is that if queen takes F5,
the knight on G3 is dropped.
And if white plays bishop takes E5, we
can take back with the rook.
And if white takes with the rook, we
again take with our rook and the F5 pawn
is protected.
Now, I realize that I've miscalculated.
I think our opponent has
Wait, no. Oh, there's a beautiful detail
at the end. Oh my gosh. I really hope
this happens.
So, what I missed after rook takes E5 is
that white can play rook takes E5.
Rook takes E5 and now rook to F1 when
there is no way for us to defend the F5
pawn.
But, we have a beautiful tactical
solution in that position.
Let's see if our opponent falls for it.
I mean, our opponent has not fallen for
much of anything thus far.
And I will admit I have gotten
outplayed, more or less. I don't think
we're worse if this tactical idea I have
generated actually works out for us. 92.
No, our opponent does not fall for it.
Okay.
So what do we do now? Yeah, rookie three
very nice.
So now I think it's a good idea for us
to
try to immediately claim
dominance over the e file. Right? The e
file is the only open file on the board.
As I've shared many many times before
when there is only one open file,
generally speaking you want to be the
one to control that file first.
So how do we do that? Well, the move
Queen E6 comes to mind.
But if you think about it carefully,
Queen E6 allows white to step into F4
with tempo. And you don't want to allow
tempo moves in an open position. So can
we do the same thing but without
allowing a tempo move?
Yeah, Queen E8 is what we're going to
play. Now Bishop H6 is a very sensible
move that some of you are suggesting as
a way to safeguard and secure the E3
square. Maybe go rookie three next. I
like Bishop H6.
But I think for the time being keeping
the bishop fianchettoed is a more
flexible approach. I think Queen E8 is a
little bit more to the point.
So let's see. It also poses white with a
decision and decisions are never fun,
especially when one side is getting low
on time.
So let's see where white goes. And
normally for you know,
players in the 1300 range, you know,
these types of decisions are very
difficult. Where to put the knight?
And notice that if the knight moves if
the knight moves away from E2,
we have the possibility of trading off
the rooks with rookie one check and that
could be beneficial to us if we
determine that the bishop is stronger
than the knight in the resulting
position, which we're going to have to
calculate based on where white puts
their knight.
Knight F4.
So, I see immediately two candidate
moves.
The first is the move rook to E3, which
everybody should see. That drives the
queen out of F3.
And it paves the way for the bishop to
drop into this very nice D4 square.
We're starting to make progress.
The second move, and the more concrete
approach to the position, is of course
to play rook E1 check. So, let's
calculate rook E1 check. Rook E1 check.
Rook takes E1.
Queen takes E1 check.
King H2.
And then in that position,
we can step into E5 with the bishop
pinning the knight.
But in that position, white can unpin
the knight by playing pawn to G3.
And
I'm just not totally convinced that
black has enough to win the game in that
position.
So, from the perspective of playing for
a win,
I think the way to do it is in fact to
play rook E3 keeping the tension.
Moreover, we have a really pretty tactic
after queen F2. I think we can win a
pawn.
I'm actually not totally convinced that
winning the pawn is the best that we can
do there.
No, queen F2 loses.
Queen F2 loses. White has to find queen
F1. Not elementary. And our opponent
blunders the queen in one move.
And again, it's consistent with
the pattern that we've kind of observed,
which is that players can play really,
really well at this level. Like really,
really well at this level.
But the moment you start putting serious
pressure and creating a lot of threats
in a row,
blunders are incredibly common.
And I I think we've seen that over and
over and over again. 95. Let's finish
the game off in style.
Obviously, do not play rook takes D3.
It's never too late to blunder. I think
a lot of you would play rook takes d3
missing the fork on e7.
So, anytime the knight is in close
proximity to the king and the queen,
you look very, very carefully at
potential forks and you keep the rook on
the e-file. Rookie 2 is a move that both
is active and protects the e7 square.
Yeah, I mean, excellent game by our
opponent. I I honestly have to say I was
pretty close to getting outplayed there.
And I think he's totally legit. I mean,
as was evidenced by queen takes c6.
So, rook f1.
Now,
again, we should be careful not to play
queen g6
walking into knight f4 with a fork.
So, we just have to sort of sidestep
these potential forks.
And I think the best way to do it
is probably, let me think for a second,
to play queen to d6. Actually, queen to
d6.
And the point is just to drive the queen
into g3.
If And that is anticlimactic, but that's
the speedrun for you. It's a mixed bag.
I'm sure we'll get our share of
thrilling finishes.
This just didn't happen to be one of
them, but that doesn't mean
there isn't plenty to talk about in this
game. There is.
Queen g3 is game over. Notice that
knight e7 check, the rook is still
protecting that square. Knight f6 check,
we play bishop takes f6.
And we basically have two sources of
threats here. There is the checkmate in
one threat, queen takes g2.
And if it's defended with knight f4,
then there's the second category of mate
threats on the back rank with rookie 1.
So, there's no way to defend against
both
threats at the same time.
And he doesn't, and we win.
And we cross 1200.
All right.
Tough game, 33 moves.
Let's analyze.
So, once again,
this is the Rossolimo,
and it is considered
not even a second it's not a sideline.
It is a main line.
Alongside the move d4, Bishop b5 is sort
of the second main line against knight
c6.
And that is why some players who play
the accelerated Dragon, they like to
start with a move g6. This is actually
called the hyper accelerated Dragon, but
there is no free lunch.
And the drawbacks of g6 greatly outweigh
the benefits. So, the drawback of the
immediate g6 is that c3 the Alapin is
actually
very, very annoying against the early
g6. In addition, white has d4, c takes
d4, and Queen takes d4, which is a whole
This is not better for white, but it's a
whole another opening that you have to
know.
So, that's why I don't recommend g6. In
the speed run, we allow the Rossolimo,
and we just learn how to play against
it.
So, as I mentioned, the two main moves
here are e6
and g6, and the way you choose a move is
based on what you play
uh traditionally, what you play against
d4.
Uh if you play e6 or e5, or you're a
Sveshnikov player, then most of the time
you play e6 and vice versa.
Which is not to say that accelerated
Dragon players are not allowed to play
e6 or that you can't learn this,
but I just think this is more consistent
with with what we normally play, if that
makes sense. So, g6.
Bishop takes c6.
Now, recently, uh
players, including Wesley So, who
recommends this in his Chessable e4
course, I myself with white, I play a
cross between the Rossolimo and the
Alapin Sicilian that is recommended by
Wesley, which is to castle,
Bishop g7, and now to play the move C3.
And this has gained a lot of steam in
recent years.
Uh in fact, I would say it's overtaken
Bishop takes C6 in popularity. This this
C3 line.
And after knight F6, white actually
usually defends the e-pawn with rook e1.
You've probably seen me play e5 in
blitz, which is a sideline, and it's
really interesting, but it's equal.
Rook e1 is a very serious attempt at an
advantage.
And here the main line goes castles.
White occupies the center with d4.
And as is so often the case, how does
black usually deal with uh this imposing
center? How does black counter strike in
the center?
Yeah, this is not the Alapin. This is a
completely different opening. This is
the Rossolimo.
So, as a Sicilian player, you should
remember
uh that
the move here is d5. Yeah, d5.
So, e Some of you're suggesting e e5 is
very awkward.
E5 is very awkward. It closes down the
bishop, and after d5,
I think you're also likely to just lose
the pawn on e5. No, this is
this just looks
Yeah, this looks awkward.
Of course, if you're not comfortable
playing d5, then you should play the
move d6.
But clearly after d6, white normally
plays h3 to stop Bishop g4.
Uh here black is slightly worse. Black
is cramped. So,
the theoretical move is actually d5.
And the idea is to carve out this very
powerful square for the knight. And you
might say, "Well, but what about the
bishop? Isn't the bishop now biting on
granite?" And it is.
And that's called a complicated
position, right? Not everything is
perfect. But later on in the game,
another idea that you should be very
familiar with when there is a pawn
chain,
ideally, you want to attack the tip uh
the the sorry, the base of the pawn
chain. But here you can't do it, right?
If you compare this kind of structure,
let's say to the advanced French. In the
advanced French, you get the same
structure, but you have the capacity of
attacking D4. You do so by piling up
with your pawns and your pieces.
Now, fast forwarding to this position,
you can't really orchestrate an
effective attack on D4. So, the next
best thing often is to
uh
break up the tip of the pawn chain,
which is not ideal, but often opens up
the piece. And that's why as many of you
are pointing out, one of Black's main
ideas in this position is indeed to push
the F pawn to F6.
Okay?
Which is not to say that Queen B6 is not
a common move in this position.
Uh
as well. It most certainly is, but F6
happens frequently as well.
Uh anyways, you can analyze this on your
own. I'm sure we'll probably get this
again
uh later on in the in the speedrun. In
this game, White plays the traditional
line, which is to trade on C6 and to
push the pawn to D3.
Okay. So, D3 is played. We played Bishop
G7. Knight C3.
And knight to F6. Now, checking
reference, I can see that E5 immediately
is also considered a viable continuation
and then developing the knight to E7.
But the problem is that knight on E7 is
heavily restricted by the pawn on E4.
Robert Hess likes to point this out in
his commentaries. For example, let's say
White castles and Black plays knight E7.
What I don't like about this position is
that the knight just has no prospect.
It's dominated by the pawn on E4.
So, that's why I wanted to reposition
the knight on a slightly better square,
the D7 square.
Um
but the main reason you play DC rather
than BC, as I explained after the game,
BC is a totally viable alternative.
There is a ton of theory in BC as well.
So again, you should always take my
opening recommendations with a grain of
salt and you should not assume that the
alternative move is somehow a mistake.
In most cases, in the first 10 12 moves,
it's just an alternative.
But DC opens up the light-squared bishop
and increases our control over key
central squares by opening up the D-file
for our queen.
So D3, bishop G7, knight C3. We decided
on knight F6, which is also very popular
move. Castles.
And we take the opportunity to bring the
bishop out to G4.
That is why
uh most grandmasters in this position
play the move H3 to keep this bishop
relatively uh confined. And black still
goes knight D7. That is still the main
line.
White normally develops the bishop.
Black plays E5 and this position has
occurred thousands of times. White is
considered to be a smidge better here,
but it's just a very strategically
complex game. Just a very strategically
complex game.
Um white plays queen D2 a lot of the
time to prepare bishop H6. Now black
prevents bishop H6 by pushing the pawn
up to H6.
Uh castles kingside.
Uh white black often plays B6 here. And
yeah, there are hundreds of games uh all
all throughout these lines. And one of
white's main ideas in this position
is actually to prepare the F pawn uh the
F4 pawn break. You often see white uh
driving the knight back, let's say
knight H2, and then quickly trying to
push F4 to open up the kingside and then
attack on the kingside. Exploiting the
fact that black cannot easily castle
kingside or uh risk dropping the pawn on
H6.
And what you will often see is that the
knight from D7, who can remind me what
is the knight's sort of ideal maneuver
from this position?
And I mentioned this during our game.
This is also very pertinent in this
position.
The knight from D7
travels to Frankfurt Airport, knight F8,
and then from F8 maneuvers to E6
with the dual purpose of controlling the
F4 square and discouraging white from
playing F4. That is why most people play
F4 here while it's not too late.
But after EF bishop F4 knight E6, the
secondary idea is to control this
all-important D4 square, which can be
used as an outpost for the knight. You
can play knight C4 on the very next
move, and there are still dozens of
games in this position.
So,
something like this
constitutes uh the sort of traditional
main line of the Rossolimo, but here our
opponent castles allowing us to uh to to
get rid of this bishop so that it
doesn't constitute a headache a little
bit later in the middle game. Hopefully,
that makes sense. So, we play knight C7.
Bishop E3, we push E5, reaching kind of
our target setup with these two pawns
clamping down on the D4 square.
And if I were playing white here, I
would probably choose
to carry out the F4 pawn break anyway.
Who can tell me a nice way that white
can prepare F4? Like, what is necessary
in order for white to play F4?
Where should the queen go? Is really
what I'm asking. No, folks, come on.
Bringing over the knight, is that
necessary? The F4 square is already
protected by the bishop, by the rook, by
potentially by the queen. So, the best
move is queen G3. You want to kind of
step the queen over to the side onto a
relatively invulnerable square.
You see a lot of players, they play, for
example, queen D1. But that move ruins
the coordination between the rooks, and
you want to keep the queen around,
right? You just want to keep it on a a
square where it doesn't interfere. Queen
G3 is the best move, castles, and white
can safely push F4.
Now here, what would black do? Well, for
black, we already know some of the
ideas. You guys can already generate a
move based on what you know. Well, what
do you know? Well, one thing that we
already know is that the knight's ideal
square is E6. So, what move prepares the
long knight maneuver?
The fool's ghost got it. You deserve a
sub. The best move according to the
engine as I see here is in fact rookie
eight. And this move should already make
perfect sense to you. First of all,
you're bringing the rook onto a better
square, obviously, and you're
controlling the E5 square. So, you might
play knight E5, but more likely, you'll
play knight F8, knight E6, and knight
D4,
as is typical.
Another move is queen B6 here, just
trying to harass the pawn on B2, and of
course exploiting the fact that white
can't push B3 uh because he loses the
knight. White has to play this awkward
move, and now you can use the x-ray
against white's king to play the move C4
check, trying to improve your queen side
pawn structure.
And if bishop E3, you can throw in the
move bishop D4. Look how active black's
pieces suddenly are. And here black has
solved all of his problems, or her
problems.
Lax Enhancer asks, "Isn't rookie eight
giving up some defense of the F4 pawn?"
Again and again and again, when you play
an opening like the Sicilian, most moves
in a complicated middle game are going
to have some drawbacks. But, to that you
should ask yourself, are you really
worried about white winning the F F7
pawn? Right, defending something isn't
an inherent good or an inherent
inherently bad thing. It's just a fact
of the position. Not defending something
doesn't, again, constitute a bad thing
if that something cannot be effectively
attacked.
So, you could say, "Well, okay,
can white attack F7?" Well, in order for
white to attack F7, white's going to
have to move their bishop out of F4.
And after bishop E3, knight F8, you just
calculate. Don't be afraid to calculate.
Well, this
drops the C5 pawn.
So, that doesn't really work, but let's
throw in the move B6.
And
okay, what if white plays queen F2? Is
this dangerous? Can we not defend F7?
Oh, we absolutely can. How should we
defend the F7 pawn? Who can tell me?
No, no, no, no, no. Don't go F6. Come
on, guys. Don't go F6. Don't go knight
E5.
The knight is earmarked for F8 and E6.
The best move is queen E7.
Rookie 7 is a little bit awkward. It's
just yeah.
It it blocks the queen. It sets up a
potential pin. So, now you can't play
knight F8 because of bishop G5.
So, the most harmonious move is queen
E7.
Notice that the pawn on C6 here
restricts the knight on C3, preventing
knight D5.
Which is actually very important.
Otherwise, knight D5 would be a problem.
So, look at how every kind of cog in the
machine is important. You have to
appreciate the placement of every piece
and how it's impacting the position,
what squares are important to control
and what squares are not important to
control.
Okay, white can play bishop G5 even
here.
But, you can just play First of all, you
can play queen E6. Second of all, I
think tactically this move actually
works.
There, there, there.
And you could play a move like bishop E5
and prepare queen G3. I mean, look at
how weak the dark squares are around
white's king. I think black has full
compensation here.
So, anyways, we kind of went far there,
but
that's what I would do with white.
Our opponent played I wouldn't say
aimlessly. I mean, our opponent played
quite quite decently.
A4, we met with A5.
And our opponent decided to maneuver the
knight to G3, which is actually a very
impressive idea for this level to to
prepare to prevent F5.
And our idea stemmed from the fact that
we want to play F5, so we bring our
queen up to E6.
White plays C3, and here we decided to
take the plunge and play F5.
Now, I'd like to point out that there
actually wasn't really any hurry. I
think in a classical game I would err on
the side of playing a move like B6
first, because there is no like instant
hurry to play F5.
I exaggerated during the game indicating
that B4 is dangerous. B4 is actually not
dangerous now that I look at it
carefully, because it does a lot more
harm than good. And after A takes B4, C
takes B4, I want to point out an
instructive idea.
So, here for black the best move is rook
takes A4.
And who can tell me the best move after
B takes C5? This is an instructive move
that you should come up with pretty
instinctively.
Yeah, so what you shouldn't do is play
BC, because your pawns are terrible.
This is like the worst extra pawn in the
world. Not to mention you'll probably
lose it back.
The best move is B5, right? Classic move
creating a protected passer,
and this is the most well-protected pawn
on the whole board.
Meanwhile, white is the one who's got
the weak pawn on C5. The bishop is tied
down to it, and you could later attack
it with queen E7.
So, this is like an important way to
uh successfully resolve the tension on
the queen side. It's better than playing
C takes B4, which is also not bad. You
could play like this.
But, if you play like this, you give the
rook a nice square on C4, and you create
for yourself a a backward pawn on B6,
which could be easily pressured by the
other rook from B1.
So, if you just consider the ways to
transform the queen side structure, rook
A4 and B5 is by far the best.
So, I would have played B6, but we
decided in the game to play more
decisively with F5. The engine actually
likes it. Takes, takes
and bishop to D2, dropping the bishop
back.
So, here we decided to move the queen in
to D5, which I think is a very
reasonable move.
Um
Flaming Cornbread asks an interesting
question, "Why not B5 to undouble the
pawns?" Well, the answer is simple.
White's not going to take on B5, right?
And you might say, "Well, then you take
on A4." But again, it's the same logic
as B takes E5 being bad. After B takes
A4, yeah, you win a pawn technically,
but look at the damage you're doing to
your pawn structure. You're damaging
your pawn structure permanently. So,
with white, I would play a move like
knight H5 here. I would just ignore the
possibility of B8. So, don't
assume that your opponent is going to
cooperate in whatever you want to do.
Um
How do you determine in that position
that you should aim for F5? Well, it's
it's a stock plan. It's a typical plan
in this position.
And well, the reason I'm able to see
that F5 is good is because attacking the
king side with your pawns is just
inherently good, as well as the fact
that it threatens F4. So, it actually
pushes white's minor pieces off of their
squares.
Um In the event of the move knight H5, I
think we would have just driven the pawn
into F4 anyway.
And notice that I modify my play based
on my opponent's move. Who can remind me
why the move F4 is positionally bad in
this situation? For example, in this and
other similar situations.
Why is F4 bad?
Because of knight E4. Yeah, and this is
a monster square, but it's a monster
square only if it's occupied by a
knight.
But, if white plays knight H5, then we
can play F4 and the knight is
excommunicated. It's out of commission.
It's trapped. So, probably white is
going to end up trading it up for the
bishop.
But now, we are more than happy to give
up the e4 square.
Because there's nothing good that can
occupy it. And furthermore, we could
even push c4 on doubling our pawns. So,
b5 actually is the right idea, but c4
forces white to take on c4 or allow c
takes d3. And there is nothing good to
occupy e4. This is a very important
concept, and it's never really too early
to understand it. It's the notion that a
weak square does not exist in a vacuum.
I call it the notion of inaccessibility,
right?
It's like if a tree falls in the forest,
did anybody hear it? If a weak square
exists and there is no piece to occupy
it with, then it's not even really a
weak square, and you shouldn't be too
worried about weakening it.
So,
you should always ask yourself like, can
my opponent access the weak square?
And can they do it in a timely fashion?
And if the answer is no, very often you
can make a move
that would otherwise be totally
unthinkable.
And
there's always a go-to example that I
indicate in this case, and I've I've
shown it during the speed run before.
Um but it's one of my favorite
illustrations of this concept.
Um and it's it's not a very well-known
game. This is a game between two very
strong GMs, as you can see. Sergey is an
Armenian GM. Tomashevsky is a Russian
GM.
2013.
And they reached the position that you
see in front of you.
So, it's it's white to move.
And the goal is to generate the best
move.
And the real goal is to Well, it's to
gain a positional advantage for white.
So, I'll give you guys a moment to think
about what black's main idea is.
And
if you listen carefully to the theme,
then the move should make perfect sense
right at the outset. White to move.
And if you're watching on YouTube, you
should similarly pause and try to
generate the move. Even if you're a
beginner,
you should still kind of understand this
concept. So,
I would encourage everybody to try.
White to move.
And some of you may remember this
position. I mean, I've shown it before,
but it's worth showing again.
So,
let's take a step back and most of you
are getting the move and figure out the
ideas for both sides, which are actually
very simple. White's attacking on the
queen side. So, white is ready to
engineer and carry out the B5 pawn break
and create major weaknesses for black on
the queen side.
Um but black, of course, is threatening
to push E5 and open up the center
exploiting eventually the weakness on
E3.
So, for example, if we were to push B5
prematurely, black would trade and play
E5.
And in the event of the trade, the
knight would then jump to C4.
And the attack on the E3 pawn would
become very unpleasant. So, Sargissian
plays the brilliant move F4.
And it's brilliant because it's
seemingly anti-positional. He closes
down the bishop, but more importantly,
he creates this gaping hole on E4.
But, of course, the key is that black
cannot physically occupy the square with
his knight. In order to do so, black
needs 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 moves to get there
with his knight.
And of course, the reason is that G5 is
not accessible and D6 is not accessible.
The two airports are closed. And in the
time that black spends trying to get his
knight there, white is already going to
break through on the queen side a
million times over, which is basically
exactly what happened. Now, I'm not
going to pretend that white is winning
after F4,
but it makes black's life incredibly
difficult.
So, this concept of something
not a weak square not being accessible
is really important and often a reason
to create that weakness in the first
place. Yeah, black cannon probably
should have played G5.
But after G5, we can ignore and we can
just play B5.
Right? Again, remember the concept of
just ignoring your opponent's pawn play.
You don't always have to engage them.
GF, you play EF.
And who does the opening of the E file
benefit? Well, it only benefits white
because there's a weak pawn that's
sitting on E6.
This game ended No, white won. White
actually did win this game.
So, let's go back to the speedrun.
Um that was a very long-winded
explanation, I admit, but I think it's a
very pertinent concept. We weaken E4
only because white no longer has a
knight that can occupy it. And in this
position, I think black is not worse.
After DC, we can even consider pushing
the other pawn with E4 and we've got a
lot of prospects for our pieces.
So, in any case,
bishop D2, queen D5, queen E2.
So, here we played the general's kind of
solidifying move, rook F7. Somewhere
around here, I think objectively I got a
worse position. I like our opponent's
move C4.
At first glance, I was very
pessimistic about it. I thought it
creates a big weakness on D4, but our
opponent's idea was very concrete and it
was to improve the placement of his
bishop and put pressure on the E5 pawn.
So now, we took a tempo to play B6. I
think this is an important move,
protecting the A5 pawn.
Rook FE1 and we bring our rook to E8.
So, this part of the game is very
logical and then we get the next stage
of the game after F4.
So, I don't think F4 is a mistake. I
think white is still doing fine here.
We played queen G6, sliding the queen to
a better defensive square and attacking
the knight.
Queen F3 is another excellent move.
We double our rooks on the E file
and I actually think that this is still
not a a mistake.
I think that the main mistake by our
opponent
uh the first like the the first serious
mistake was to play this move 92.
Because it it it yields without a fight
control of the e-file and it lets us
play Queen E8 with tempo. And this is a
big tempo move. It's still I think the
position is equal with best defense, but
it gets unpleasant here already.
So in any case um
I think
probably
if white wanted to play accurately then
in this position white should have
refrained from releasing the tension
with F takes E5 cuz that really allowed
us to
uh you know get rid of the problem of
this passive knight. And we won the
battle over the e-file. So probably
white's best move is something like
Rookie 2. This is an incredibly hard
move.
I mean this is a grandmaster level move.
Because white's just trying to double on
the e-file and white's trying to win the
damn battle over the e-file, but a lot
of players would be worried about the
look of the move E4 I think.
94 looks a little scary, but if you
calculate after FE4 D4 FE4
white actually has a beautiful tactical
idea. It's a gorgeous tactical idea.
I'll let you guys try to find it.
White to play.
Not F5. F5 doesn't work
because after E takes F3 F takes G. So
you have to take the queen and then you
give up the rook.
But you're close. The correct sequence
does involve the move F5.
Now if you think about it, what does the
move F5 achieve? Well, it attacks white
black's queen. It also cuts off the
connection between the queen and the E4
square. So think about what you can
start with.
The key is to eliminate the attack on
white's queen. Then F5 is going to work.
The move is knight takes E4. Yeah, very
close. Rook takes E4 is also good by the
way, but 94 is even better.
And the idea is to meet rook takes E4
with F5 and white is winning.
Because the queen hangs.
Black can't get a lot for the queen. And
if the queen moves, then there's no way
to move the queen and simultaneously
defend the rook. Black wins. Uh white
wins.
Here, here.
And white is up an exchange.
So, maybe beautiful was an
overstatement, but still very, very nice
idea.
But, you kind of would have to see that
when playing rookie 2.
And if black plays E takes F4, then you
can just play rookie 7 rookie 7 queen
F4. And you might say, "Well, but didn't
white give up the E file here?" Well,
yes, but here there's the extenuating
circumstance that the F5 pawn is now a
massive weakness. And black might even
have to get away from the E file to
defend it.
But, this just shows you how beautiful
positional chess is and how intertwined
tactics are with strategy, right? That
there's a strategic plan here of
controlling a file, but the way that you
control it is you actually use these
super complicated tactics. That's why
positional chess is really hard.
Now, a lot of you were asking me to
analyze the move knight H5.
Uh knight H5, I just did analyze. We We
We looked at it just now.
Uh a couple of moves ago. And we
determined that I would have played F4.
Of course, there were other moments when
white could have played the move knight
H5. And not in all of those moments
would we have responded with F4.
Like, for example, if white plays knight
H5 here, I'm already not Well, I guess
still F4.
I still think F4 is very good to trap
the knight and potentially prepare F3.
Yeah, we would have still played F4.
And even here probably we would have
played F4.
So, this F4 mechanism was very strong
provided that the knight wouldn't be
able to reach E4.
So, back we go to bishop E5 rookie 5
rookie 5. There was a beautiful tactic
here that I had noticed. And it was in
response to rook F1, which actually I
think rook F1 was still the best move.
And maybe the only remaining way to
to to get equality.
The move as many of you indicated is
rook to E3.
And the idea is queen takes E3, bishop
D4. The game is not over.
How should white proceed here? Well,
white should give up the queen for the
bishop and snag another pawn. White is
rook, knight, and pawn for the queen,
but in such an open position the queen
is able very often to infiltrate uh the
opponent's camp, and I think black is
winning here. Or at least black has good
winning chances.
But who can spot the brilliant counter
move by white?
The Well, the tactics aren't over here.
White has a defense.
I know some of you must be thinking
knight takes F5, but that's not the
move.
I read people's mind.
Knight F5 is not the move if you
actually calculate.
Queen C6 blunders the queen still.
Yeah, the move is actually queen takes
F5. Only move.
Knight F5 is very creative,
but a lot of people just kind of stop
calculating here. Assuming, "Oh, I win
the queen back." But it's not enough to
win the queen back because black just
goes king F7.
If you take the rook with check, then
you give up the piece that's attacking
the queen. And if you take the queen,
bishop D4 is even stronger, but the
simple rook F1 and H3 just wins the game
on the spot.
So,
that doesn't cut it. Queen takes F5. The
idea is that the queen pays a visit to
C8 with checkmate in the event that
black takes on G3 with either piece.
So, black actually has to trade queens
and win the pawn back,
but I think this rook end game if white
defends it carefully is a draw. In fact,
even if white doesn't defend it
carefully, this is just a draw.
Because the pawn end game is losing for
black
because of the deep freeze. So, black
has to keep the rooks on the board, and
now white's managed to kind of defend
everything.
So,
this I think was the narrow drawing
line. But, if we our opponent had seen
that, then I would have been a little
bit suspicious.
92 Queen E8 knight F4 rook E3, and I
already think that white is losing here.
So, people watching on YouTube and
thinking that the game was
anticlimactic, in fact, it's already
like minus three.
And the reason is that the queen has no
good squares.
Queen F2 loses almost immediately
because it aligns the king and the
queen, allowing bishop D4, devastating
move. And there's no way to stop all the
discoveries. White loses the queen.
Um Flaming Cornbread is asking a
question, "Why not rook E1 check?"
Oh, why not rook E1 check takes here and
here? Well, because queen takes C6.
And I'm afraid that black will not be
able to escape the perpetual. The king
is too weak here. The queen has too many
checks.
So, this just seemed way too drawish.
And remember that we considered bishop
E5 G3, and I also think this is maybe
only slightly better for
uh for black.
So, rook E3 is definitely the move.
White should have played Queen F1.
But here, we don't even really need to
do anything specific. The computer's top
move is actually just bishop to F6.
And the idea is to maneuver the bishop
to this beautiful square on G3 where it
kind of maximally restricts white's
position and sets up ideas of rook E1.
So, bishop F6 actually was incredibly
strong here, and white is already
essentially paralyzed. The knight has no
squares. It is literally restricted by
all of black's pieces. This is
incredibly bad for white. Yeah, we can
play bishop D4 also, but then white
moves the king away.
And while the bishop looks incredibly
good on D4, it would be better placed on
G3
because it would be doing a lot more
specific things.
So, another grandmaster move, bishop to
F6 H4 and G3.
How do you know that you have time for
this? Well, because white is out of
moves. And the reason white is out of
moves is because you control the only
open file. That's the power of that.
So,
yeah, queen c6, a disappointing blunder
for sure, and we won't analyze after
this, but
uh
the main mistake actually was this
knight e2 knight f4 maneuver. That's
what lost white the game.
That really was all that it was. It was
like two knight moves on move
27 and 28.
So, if our opponent had played rook f1,
the game would have still been
relatively balanced, but that would
involve finding this incredible tactic
with queen f5.
So, one interesting kind of narrative
that you saw in that game is that it's
not like white you know, white's
position deteriorated very, very
quickly, but that's from a purely
objective standpoint. If you reason
practically, white made some
inaccuracies earlier in the game that
set him up for this. So, for example,
already fe was an inaccuracy. You could
even argue that f4 was a pretty risky
move that got the game very tactical.
And it increased the probability that
you know, stuff was going to go down and
a mistake would essentially lose the
game. And that is the
oftentimes the difference between open
positions positions with an open center,
positions with a closed center. In a
position with a closed center, you don't
really run the risk of losing the game
if you make a small mistake or you put
your piece on the wrong square. That's
why some people prefer you know, to play
closed positions because
you know, there's less at stake with
every mistake as opposed to wide open
center positions with lots of tactics.
Um
so, in any case, that was the game. It
was a really rich positional game,
you know, even though it it ended up
being pretty short.
So, I feel like I talked a lot, but I
hope you found it productive.
Um
and that's yet another entry in our
speedrun opening theme speedrun as we
start encountering more principled
openings. I think we're already starting
to build our understanding of key
typical positions. Remember that like
training middle games is actually an
extension of training openings. You have
to know key middle game ideas. That's
why in this game I put a big emphasis on
explaining the logic behind
DC and like E5 and these are all moves
that we're going to play again in the
Ruy Lopez.
Uh but I'm pretty exhausted. That took a
lot of my energy.
I hope you can appreciate that.
And I'm going to hit the sack.
And thanks everybody
for watching. Thanks for hanging out and
again, subscribing to the YouTube. It
really helps keep the content going.
Um that's how I make a living. So
you know.
So I would really appreciate it and uh
Thanks everybody. See you tomorrow. Bye.